Now, the sword hunt that Togame the Strategian and the 7th generation Kyotouryuu head Yasuri Shichika have been on...
さて　奇策士とがめと虚刀流七代目鑢七花の刀集めも
has been ongoing for 4 months, and it is now April.
４カ月に及び　卯月のころ
ここは周防の外れにある とある小さな村でございます
We are now in a certain small village on the outskirts of Suou, in the eastern Yamaguchi prefecture.
桜吹雪の舞い散る夜
On this night where sakura petals dance like falling snow,
とがめは村長が差し出してくれた　仮の宿へと急いでおります
Togame is hurrying towards the temporary lodgings which the village mayor had provided them.
That Sabi Hakuhei is just so...
錆白兵め
まったく　どこまでも
Shichirin!
しちりん
Shichirin, wake up!
しちりん　起きろー
I'm not sleeping, and what's with that name?
寝てないよつーか　その呼び方
「俺は炭を燃料に使うこんろかよ」とでも言いたいか
"What am I, some portable stove or something?" is what you want to say, right?
いいか　この呼び方はだな
This is why I used that nickname —
いつも言っているようにそなたがバカで個性も薄く
As I'm always saying, you're an idiot, you have no individuality, no flair, you mess your lines up, and your acting is garbage, so...
しかも華もなくせりふもかみかみで
芝居もダメダメだなところをだなあ
This is a hassle, and I'm tired...
めんどくさ　疲れた
You look it.
みたいだな
言ってくれれば俺だって手伝うのに
If you had just asked me, I would have helped out.
幕府の使いに会うのはわたしの役目だ
It's my duty to meet with messengers that the Shogunate sends.
I see.
そうか
明日の朝　村長にあいさつしたら出発するぞ
We're leaving tomorrow morning after we say goodbye to the village mayor.
あした
Tomorrow?
意外と早いな
That's pretty fast...
しばらくはここで報告を待つんじゃなかったのか
Weren't we going to settle here for a while and wait for reports of that Sabi Hakuhei guy?
錆白兵ってやつのこと
そのことで今夜幕府からの使いの者と話してきたのだが
I was talking about him with the Shogunate's messenger just now.
I didn't have to look far...
探るまでもなかった
はい？
What?
Sign: Letter of Challenge
錆のやつ　われわれが張り付かせた尾行者に気付き
Sabi noticed the man we had following him, and handed over a letter of challenge, of all things.
あろうことか　自分から堂々と果たし状を渡してきたようだ
まったくどこまでも古風なやつだ
My goodness...
How old-fashioned can you get?
Hakutou
Hari
Well, give it a read.
まあ　読んでみろ
読めない
I can't read.
俺平仮名は読めないんだ
I can't read Japanese Hiragana.
まあいい　要約すればこうだ
Well, whatever.
To summarize, he said:
"I challenge you to a duel for the Shikizaki Kiki Swords."
「四季崎記紀の刀を賭けて　勝負だ」
Straight to the point.
ずいぶんと真っすぐだなあ
Yeah.
The more I think it over, the stranger it sounds.
聞けば聞くほどおかしな話だぜ
He's such an old-fashioned, straight guy,
そんな古風で真っすぐな男が
とがめひいては忠義を尽くすべき幕府を刀欲しさに裏切っただなんて
and yet he betrayed you and the Shogunate which he was loyal to, simply out of desire for a sword?
It's not such a strange notion when you consider he was touched by the poison of Shikizaki's swords.
四季崎の刀の毒のなせる技だ
The sword's poison...
刀の毒なあ
剣士であればあるほど
The more pure a swordsman you are, the more the poison affects you.
その毒は体中に回るのだ
Deeply, very deeply...
深く深くな
He's a man who lost most of his humanity after devoting too much of himself to swordsmanship.
剣士であり過ぎるが故に
人らしさをほとんど失った男だからな
見た目こそ女と見まごうような総髪の美少年だが
His looks and that knotted hairstyle might even trick you into thinking he's a woman,
空に浮かぶ月ですら真っ二つにできるという触れ込みだ
but he's reputed to be able to cut even the moon clean in half.
Shichirin, hold my hair up for me or it's going to tangle.
しちりん　髪がもつれる持ち上げていてくれ
It seems that Sabi knows about the swords we have.
錆は俺たちが刀を手に入れていることを知っているみたいだな
At the very least, he knows about Kanna and Namakura.
少なくとも鉋と鈍についてはそうであろうな
それにあれから１カ月過ぎている
And it's been a month since we obtained Tsurugi,
つるぎのことを知られていたとしても不思議ではない
so it wouldn't be strange if he knew about that by now too.
The fact that this man doesn't seem to know desire for women probably isn't just because he grew up on a deserted island.
この男が劣情を催さぬのは
無人島育ちだからというだけではないだろう
We must be leaking information if Sabi knows about our swords.
俺たちの刀は
That aspect of him is why he was able to kill our third foe, Tsuruga Meisai, so easily.
だからこそ
七花は３番目の敵
敦賀迷彩をあっさり殺した
He has no qualms about killing women.
女を殺すのに抵抗を覚えない
男女を区別しない
He doesn't even distinguish between men and women.
That being the case, why has this man, this sword, fallen for me?
それならばこの男 この刀
わたしのいったいどこにほれたのだろう
Togame?
とがめ
What?
何だ
だから　俺たちの刀のことを錆が知ってるってことは
Like I said, the fact that Sabi knows about the swords we have means that information is leaking from somewhere.
どっかから情報が漏れてるんだねって
Y-Yeah...
There are talkative people anywhere you go.
どこにでも口の軽いやからはおるでな
Also, when it comes to a swordsman like Sabi,
それに錆ぐらいの剣士になれば
その腕に心酔し
you'll find that countless people want to help him out of admiration for his skills.
役に立とうとする者が後を絶たぬ
His outstanding strength has the tendency to charm people like that.
ずば抜けた強さというのは
それだけ人を魅了するのだ
そんなに強いのか
Is he that strong?
Truthfully speaking, I wanted to put off the fight between you and Sabi until later on...
正直わたしとてそなたと錆をぶつけるのはもう少し先にしたかったのだが
事がこう運んでしまえば致し方ないな
But now that it's comes to this, we have no choice.
わたしもできる限り知恵を絞るから
I'll put my knowledge to full use, so you just focus on putting in your best effort.
そなたはただひたすら全力を尽くせ
On top of that, Hakutou Hari is...
その上　薄刀針は
Needle - The Light
thin, frail, and above all, a beautiful sword.
薄くもろくそして何より美しい刀だ
It's going to be tough getting such a frail sword without breaking it.
そんなもろい刀折らないように集めんの大変だな
Don't concern yourself too much with the sword itself this time.
そなた今回ばかりはあまり刀そのものにこだわらぬ方がよいぞ
錆白兵とはそれだけの実力を備えた剣士だ
Sabi Hakuhei's level of swordsmanship will require your full attention.
His reputation as Japan's strongest is no bluff, no matter what sword he's using.
使う刀が何であれ
やつの日本最強の名ははったりでも酔狂でもないのだ
Do you really have to call him "strongest"?
最強　とまで言うか
Yes, he's—
ああ　あいつは
とがめ　俺の前でほかの刀のことを褒めるな
Togame, don't praise other swords in front of me!
I don't know if Sabi is the strongest or whatever, but Kyotouryuu considers itself the strongest swordsmanship.
錆がどれだけ最強なのか知らないが
虚刀流だって一応は最強の剣術をうたってるんだ
俺にだってあんたの刀としての誇りがある
I have my own pride as your sword.
それ以上にその気位を刺激されちゃ　困る
It bothers me when you poke at my self respect like that!
M-My collarbone...
っていうか鎖骨　鎖骨ヤバい
Collarbone is bad! I'm weak there!
鎖骨弱い
だから　鎖骨から手を放せ
Take your hands off it!
くてっとなる
It tickles, it tickles!
くてっとなっちゃう　やめてやめてやめて
Stop stop stop! Please!
そんなに強くは握ってないぞ
I'm not gripping you that hard.
Please... stop...
お願いだから
I'm just gently stroking—
むしろ優しくなでて
Yan yan!
やん　やん
Yan yan?
Y
A
N
Y
A
N
That's even worse!
それがむしろまずい
いいから放せ
Let go!
Ahh this is bad.
本当にヤバい　ごめん　ごめん　謝るから
I'm sorry! I apologize!
I don't get you at all, Togame.
よく分からんなあとがめは
そなたにだけは言われたくない
I don't want to hear that from you!
そなたのそういうところが錆白兵に対してもいいように働けばよい
Anyway, I hope that pride of yours works to our advantage against Sabi Hakuhei.
He's strong, you know.
錆は手ごわいぞ
Come to think of it, if I defeat him, that makes me the strongest in Japan, right?
考えてみれば
そいつを倒せば俺が日本最強になれるってことだろう
That doesn't sound bad.
悪い話じゃねえな
I suppose so...
そういうことになるんだろうが
Do you want that title?
そなたそんな称号が欲しいのか
よし　帯を結べはいはい
All right, tie my sash.
Okay.
Of course the title of "Japan's Strongest" is enticing to me.
そりゃ日本最強の称号は確かに魅力的だぜ
剣士として刀としてあんたの役にも立てようってもんだ
As a swordsman and as a sword, it means I'm useful to you.
ちょっと意外だな
That's a little surprising.
So, did you accept the duel?
で　果たし合いは受けたのかあ
Yes.
I'll think up a plan to defeat him on the way to the designated site.
やつを倒すための策は果たし合いの場所までの道中考えることにする
Where is it?
場所はどこなんだ
巌流島だ
Ganryuu Island.
巌流島
Ganryuu Island...
That's the place where the legendary duel between Musashi and Kojirou took place over 100 years ago.
１００年以上前
その地で行われた長刀と二刀との決戦ぐらい
無刀とはいえ剣士であるそなたも知っておろう
As a Kyotouryuu swordsman even you must know of it.
An island, huh...
島か
Speaking of which, I wonder how Nee-chan is doing...
そういえば　姉ちゃんどうしているかな
But I still don't understand it at all.
しかし　何度考えても解せんな
To think that in the span of just a few months, three Maniwa Corps heads have been killed...
たった数カ月の間に真庭忍軍の頭領が３人も命を落とすとは
There's no mistaking that Koumori-san, Shirasagi-san, and Kuizame-san were killed fighting over the swords.
蝙蝠さん　白鷺さん　喰鮫さんが
刀の取り合いに敗れて殺されているのは疑いもない事実です
I heard that the Maniwa Corps are being called the underdogs now.
真庭忍軍はかませ犬呼ばわりされてるらしいじゃないか
Especially after Kuizame-dono...
特に喰鮫殿なんて　迷彩ってやつに瞬殺されたって話だし
Apparently he was killed instantly by a woman called Meisai...
このままだと　俺たちの立場はますます悪くなるな
At this rate, our reputation will only get worse.
刀集めというか　虚刀流にかかわった途端に…ですよ
It started the moment we got involved with the sword gathering, or rather, with Kyotouryuu.
It feels like fate has abandoned our Maniwa Corps village.
どうも真庭の里は運に見放されたような気がします
だよな　先行きが不安だ
Yeah...
I'm worried about our future.
Are you having second thoughts?
後悔しておるのか
Would you rather have just kept on making a living by doing as the Owari Shogunate says?
主らあのまま唯々諾々と
尾張幕府の言いなりになる生活を続けていきたかったとでも
No way.
まさか
後悔などしていませんよ
I have no regrets.
ただし
It's just...
The way things are going now, with Maniwa taking all the losses, it's a disgrace to our name.
このままやられっ放しというのは真庭忍軍の名折れです
That strategian must be laughing her heart out right now.
奇策士さんは今ごろ高笑いをしておられるのではありませんか
The moment we left her, Maniwa went downhill.
自分から離れた途端 真庭は落ち目になったと
It's a pretty pitiful situation.
実際情けないかぎりだぜ
しかし　すぐに高々になったその鼻を明かしてやるぜ
But we'll wipe the smile off her face soon.
Gentlemen, don't be mistaken here.
主ら　思い違いをするでないぞ
The strategian is of no importance to us.
奇策士などわたしらにとっては関係ない
問題は虚刀流の方なのだ
Our problem is Kyotouryuu.
Kyotouryuu...
虚刀流
あの大乱の英雄か
That hero of the rebellion, huh...
俺らもずいぶん仕事をしたが英雄とは呼ばれないな
We've done quite a lot of work too, but we don't get called heroes.
There will never be a time when Ninja are hailed as heroes.
忍びが英雄になれる時代なんてありませんよ
それに英雄と呼ばれたのは虚刀流当主六代目で
Also, the "hero" was the 6th generation Kyotouryuu head.
The man we're dealing with is his son, the 7th generation head.
僕らが相手をするのは その息子の七代目ですから
The young are troublesome.
若い方がやっかいだぜ
怖いもの知らずだからな お前みたいに
They don't know fear, much like you.
Oh not at all,
いえいえ　僕はそれほどのものではありませんよ
I'm not that bold.
I merely came along to observe the ninja arts you two use for future reference.
今回も後学のために
お二人の忍法を見物させてもらいについてきた次第です
Oh, so you don't mind getting no share of the spoils then?
ほう　なら分け前はなしということでいいのだな
We were going to divide up the swords between us after defeating Kyotouryuu,
虚刀流を倒して変体刀を１本ずつ
分けるという話であったが蜜蜂がそういうつもりなら
but if you say so, Mitsubachi...
いや　それは話が別ですよ
No, that's a different matter...
あれを見ろ
Look over there.
It's the island.
島だ
あと一またぎだな
Just a stride away.
As expected of "Chouchou the Weightless".
さすがは無重の蝶々ですね
Even with us on your shoulders, this distance is just "a stride".
われわれを肩に乗せても
この程度の距離なら一またぎですか
No, even I'm getting tired.
いや　さすがの俺も疲れてんだぜ
Riding you is a strange feeling no matter how many times I do it.
何度体験してもおかしな感覚ではあるがな
Let us proceed.
では　行こう
Fly like a butterfly, sting like a bee, and consume like a praying mantis.
蝶のように舞い
蜂のように刺し
カマキリのように喰らう
真庭忍軍　虫組
Maniwa Corps: Insect Squad!
Proud and coming through!
大手を振ってまかり通る
Bye!
まだねえ
Your idea to pretend to be traveling performers was great!
なり切り旅芸人とはさすがとがめ
Nobody suspected us with these outfits.
この格好で怪しまれることないもんな
The children loved it too.
子供たちもあんなに喜んでるし
Well, I suppose we can use this act from time to time.
まあ　何だな
これからもこういうときはこの手で切り抜けよう
Let's hurry.
先を急ぐぞ
I've been thinking, after what you said last night...
いや　昨日のそなたの言葉引っ掛かってな
If Sabi knows we've collected three swords,
錆のやつがわれわれが刀を３本集めたことを知っているというなら
同様に真庭忍軍が動いてもおかしくない
then there's a good chance the Maniwa Corps will also make a move.
They could be going ahead of us to face Sabi.
やつら　わたしたちの先を越して錆の元へ行っているかもしれん
Wouldn't that be bad?
それヤバいんじゃないのか
Geez, what kind of island is this?
まったく　なんて島だ
It's like this whole thing's a mountain.
まるで島全体が山みたいだ
蝙蝠さんはここでああ
This is where Koumori-san...
Yeah.
Um...
あの
もしかして蝙蝠さん
Is it possible that Koumori-san accepted the strategian's offer with the intent to betray her from the start?
最初から奇策士さんを裏切るつもりで誘いに乗ったのでしょうか
He may have been thinking about the needs of the village.
困窮している里のことを考えていたのかもしれんな
あの刀売ればそれ相当の金になる
That sword would sell for a considerable amount of money.
Koumori-dono's hopes aside, Insect Squad's current objective is to work together to defeat Kyotouryuu and take the swords.
蝙蝠殿の思惑がどうであれ
今のわれら虫組の目的は力を合わせて虚刀流を倒し刀を奪うことだ
Well, that strategian has no family, but the 7th Kyotouryuu head has an older sister.
まっ　あの奇策士は天涯孤独の身だが
虚刀流の七代目には姉がいる
それを島に１人残しておくってのは何とも甘い
Leaving her here alone on this island was far too careless of them.
That's true.
そうですね
僕たち忍者はひきょう卑劣が売り物ですから
We ninja thrive on unfair play.
Yeah.
So, who's going to be in charge of capturing the lady?
で　どっちがその女の拉致を担当するんだ
If possible, I'd like to rest for a bit.
できれば　俺は半時ばかり休ませてもらいたい
It took longer to reach the island than I thought it would.
この島　目測よりもちょっと遠かったわ
僕が行きましょうか
Shall I go, then?
いや わたしが行くとしよう
No, I will.
Why don't you let Mitsubachi do a bit of work?
ちっとは蜜蜂にも仕事させてやらねえとよ
いや　その娘も虚刀流であることに違いあるまい
Make no mistake, that girl is also of Kyotouryuu blood.
It's best for a ninja combat specialist such as myself to go face her.
ならば最も戦闘向きの忍法を使うわたしが出向くのが上等であろう
Well, you are the leader of the Insect Squad,
まあ虫組の指揮官はあんただから判断は任せるけどさ
so we'll let you make the call.
蜜蜂はいいのかい
Mitsubachi, you're okay with that?
Yes, we can leave it to him.
はい　お任せします
You seriously have no ambition, do you?
お前は本当に欲がねえなあ
I'm surprised you keep your position as one of the Maniwa heads.
それでよく頭領が務まんな
I'll leave behind my red crystal, just in case.
一応臙脂水晶を置いていく
If anything goes wrong, you two must complete the task.
わたしにもしものことがあったら　主らが任務を果たすのだぞ
"If anything goes wrong"?
もしものこと
That's not something I'd expect "Kamakiri the Headhunter" to say.
首狩りの蟷螂と呼ばれるあんたにそれほど似合わない言葉はないな
That's right.
そうですよ
変なこと言わないでください　蟷螂さん
Please don't say weird things, Kamakiri-san.
では　参る
I'll be going, then.
That girl, huh...
あの娘か
It seems it's a good thing I came.
どうやら　わたしが来てよかったようだな
Chouchou aside, that young Mitsubachi would probably fall for her.
蝶々ならともかく
若い蜜蜂では
あっけなく心を奪われていたかもしれん
Should I aim for her feet or her arms?
狙うのは足か　腕だ
Ninpou: Tsume Awase.
Note: Claw Joint
忍法　爪合わせ
I wonder how Shichika's doing...
七花　どうしているのかしら
I told Togame-san I'd stay behind to protect the Yasuri household,
とがめさんに鑢家を守るためにここに残るなんて言っちゃったけど
but father is dead, and Shichika left...
父さんが死んで　七花が出ていって
I really am alone now.
本当にわたし独りなのよね
Kamakiri-dono sure is late...
蟷螂殿遅えなあ
Really?
そうですか　まだそれほど時間たってませんよ
It hasn't been that long.
I guess...
そうかぁ
Hey!
って　おい
You just cheated!
お前　今　インチキしただろ！
ほら　ここ
Right here!
自分に有利に　動かしたろ
You moved that stone to your advantage!
I did no such thing!
してませんよそんなこと
That's not playing fair, Mitsubachi!
ずりーなあ　ずりーよ蜜蜂
I really didn't!
ホントにしてないですから
There's no point trying to commit suicide.
自決されようとしても無駄ですよ
I removed your poison molar while you were sleeping.
奥歯に仕込んであった毒は
あなたが気絶している間に没収させてもらいましたから
重ねて申し訳ありませんが
I apologize once again,
これから　あなたを拷問しようと思っています
but I'm afraid I'm going to have to torture you now.
Maybe I'll go check on him after all.
やっぱ俺ちょっと様子見てくるわ
Something feels wrong....
何か　変な感じが
No way!
まさか　蟷螂さんにかぎって
Nothing could happen to Kamakiri-san.
I must be imagining things.
思い過ごしだな
はい
Yeah...
What should we play next?
じゃあ　次　何やるかな
Let's see...
そうですねえ
The reason I bought you here is because your companion is currently buried over there.
ここにお連れしたわけはそこにあなたのお仲間が埋まっているからです
My brother buried him.
弟が埋めたのです　確か真庭蝙蝠さんとかおっしゃいましたか
I believe he said his name was Maniwa Koumori.
So basically, I intend to do you the good will of burying you beside your companion.
つまりあなたが死んだら同じ場所に埋めて差し上げるという配慮を
わたしなりに示したつもりですが
You have the choice, so why don't you pick?
せっかくだから選んでいただけないでしょうか
「選ぶ」とは何を
Choice? Pick what?
わたしに何を選べというのか
What do you want me to choose?
Whether to keep silent then die, or talk then die.
だから黙って死ぬか　しゃべって死ぬか
Though, I don't really mind which one you pick.
わたしは別にどちらでも構わないのですが
That said, I'm not entirely sure how to torture,
とはいえ拷問というのはいまいち勝手が分かりませんし
こう言っては何ですが
so I suppose it might be better for me if you were to stay silent and die.
正直黙って死んでいただけた方が助かる　というのはありますね
あなたに聞くべきことなどそれほど数があるわけではありませんし
There isn't all that much I need to ask you, and I already have a good idea of the general situation.
何もかも大まかには推測が立ちます
Maniwa Corps...
真庭忍軍
That's a bit long so I think I'll call you "Maniwani".
長いですから「まにわに」と呼ぶことにしましょう
That's more cute and charming.
かわいくてすてきです
From the fact that you Maniwani came to this island,
そのまにわにの方がこの島にやって来たということは
I suppose I can assume that Shichika and Togame-san's sword hunt must be well under way.
七花ととがめさんの刀集めの旅が順調に進んでいるということですね
So, how many swords have they collected so far?
で　今何本ですか
Two, or rather, including the Zettou Kanna they picked up here, three.
２本　いや
この島で収集した「絶刀 鉋」を合わせれば
３本ということになろう
That sounds like quite an easygoing journey they're taking...
それは　まあのんびりとした旅なのですね　そんなもんですか
So that's how it is...
I have yet to meet or even see your brother,
わたしはまだ主の弟に会ったことも直に見たこともないが
but as the family head, can I presume he is stronger than you?
当主ということは　七花は主よりも強いのか
ああいえ　どうでしょうね
I wonder about that...
I haven't had a proper contest with Shichika for about a year now.
ここ１年ほど七花とはまともに手合わせをしておりませんから
And on top of that, I never received training in Kyotouryuu from the former head.
それにわたしは先代より虚刀流の手解きは受けておりませんので
So what was that you used earlier on me?
では先ほど使ったあの技は　虚刀流の剣技ではないのか
That wasn't a Kyotouryuu skill?
Well I suppose it was...
それはまあ　そうなのですが
あれは返し技の一つで
That was a disarmament counter called "Patrinia".
女郎花といい　奪刀術の一種です
っていうかどうしてわたしの方が質問されてて
Wait, why are you asking me questions,
しかも　何でわたしもきちんと答えてるんですか
and why am I answering them?
No idea.
さあ
わたしからお聞きします
Let me ask then.
ここへは何人でいらしたんですか
How many of your people are here?
あなたのほかに　何人
How many besides you?
You cheated! You cheated again!
ずるした　またずるした
Cheated?
ずるって
その賽の目を忍法で変えたんだろ！
You used Ninpou to change the face of the die!
もう　そんな手品みたいな忍法僕使いませんよ
I can't do any magic tricks like that!
Strange question. I came alone, of course.
妙な問いだ
むろんわたし１人で来た
We don't have the kind of manpower in the village to send more than one soldier after a single girl.
女一人を拉致するのに人数を使うほど
真庭の里に人間は余っておらん
Kidnapping me isn't the end of your plan,
わたしを拉致してそれでおしまいというわけではないのですから
so I wouldn't be surprised if you had brought more people.
複数で来ていても変だとは思いませんよ
For instance, let's see...
そうですね
例えば　七花が集めている刀の数と同じ　３人とか
The same number as the swords Shichika carries — three.
It would help if you would tell me how many there are and what skills they possess.
人数とそれぞれが使う忍法を教えてくれたら助かるんですけど
Ah, by "would help" I mean would help me, not help your situation.
あっ今の「助かる」はわたしが助かるということで
あなたの命が助かるという意味合いではありませんので
くれぐれも誤解なきよう
I wouldn't want you to misunderstand now.
Let me tell you a bit about my brother...
弟の話ですけど
A long time ago he had a habit of biting his fingernails.
昔あの子はつめをかむ癖がありましてね
「上品ではないからやめなさい」と言ってもなかなか聞かず
It wasn't elegant so I told him to stop, but he wouldn't listen and kept biting them.
とにかくつめをかみ続けるんです
His thumb became all ragged after a while.
親指なんてぼろぼろになってしまって
だからわたしはあるときあの子のつめを全部はいであげたのですよ
So one day I tore out all his nails.
そうしたら　あの子はそれ以来つめをかむのをやめました
Ever since then, he's never bitten his nails.
Though, this is a story about child discipline, so I don't know how applicable it is as torture...
まあ幼少時代のしつけの話ですから
一概に拷問と一緒くたにするのはどうかと思いますが
あなたの場合　順序を逆にしてみましょうか
But how about we go in reverse for you?
Bite them.
かんでみなさい
どうしました
What's wrong?
子供に戻った気分で自分のつめをかめばいいと言っているのです
I said bite your nails so you can feel like a kid again.
You might cut your tongue a little,
少し舌を傷めるかもしれませんが
何もしゃべらない舌なんて不要でしょ
but you're not using it to talk anyway so it doesn't matter right?
W-Wait!
まっ　待て分かった
Fine...
"Fine"?
「分かった」とは
I mean I'll talk...
だからしゃべる俺たちの忍法は
Our Ninpou...
Ninpou...
忍法　忍法　忍法
Ninpou: Tsume Awase!
忍法　爪合わせ
すみません　動きを封じました
Sorry, I've sealed your movements now.
You deliberately used your kimono!
わざと　着物に
Well, I suppose.
ええ　まあ
Those eyes...
その目
Please forgive me, Nanami.
この父を許せ　七実
The 7th Kyotouryuu head will be Shichika.
虚刀流七代目は　七花に決めた
With this, I have no choice but to retire from active duty.
こうなってしまえば　俺はもう現役を引退せざるを得まい
While I do have some regrets, as a proud sword I will accept my fate.
心中思うところはないでもないが
しかし俺も誇り高き一本の刀として
これも定めとあきらめよう
I will accomplish my duty in passing Kyotouryuu onto the next generation.
俺は今このときより
虚刀流を後の世に伝える役目を全うしようと思う
From now on, Shichika,
これから　七花には俺の命が尽きるまで
until my life runs out,
until this body rots away,
俺の体が朽ちるまで俺の刃が錆びるまで
until my blade rusts,
I will carve all of Kyotouryuu into your body.
虚刀流の全てをお前の体にたたき込む
Forgive me, Nanami.
許せ　七実
I really wanted to have you succeed me as the head of Kyotouryuu, but that is not possible.
本音を言えば　お前に虚刀流を継いでほしいと思う
しかし　それは不可能なのだ
Understand that the impossible is impossible.
分かってくれ
無理なものは無理なのだ
Not because you are a woman, or because of your weak body, Nanami.
お前が女だからでも病弱だからでもない
七実　俺にはお前のような
But because I am unable to raise someone as exceptionally powerful as you.
例外的に強い人間を育てることはできないのだ
You have the same eyes as father did when he looked at me then...
父さんがわたしを見るときの目と 同じ
I'm tired.
疲れた
もとより忍者が拷問ごときで情報を売るとは思ってなかったけど
I hadn't thought I'd be able to extract information from a ninja using torture anyway...
それでも　さすがと言うべきなのかしら
Maybe I should say, "as expected"?
かまをかけても　全然引っ掛かってくれなかったし
I tried to trick you into confessing, but it didn't work at all.
まっ　でもだいたい想像どおりね
Well, things are pretty much as I imagined though.
Goodness, Shichika...
七花ったらあれからまだ２本しか刀を集めてないなんて
Only two swords after all this time?
You really are being lazy.
ホントのんきなんだから
When you come back I'll have to discipline you.
帰ったらお仕置きだわ
I've only ever fought with Nee-chan once.
俺 一度だけ姉ちゃんと手合わせしたことがあるんだけど
引き分けね
Looks like a draw.
Sorry, with my body I can only go for so long.
ごめんね　わたしの体力的なことで時間制限ありにしちゃって
But you did pretty well.
でも なかなかよかったわよ
I wonder whether Sabi or Nee-chan is stronger...
錆と姉ちゃん　どっちが強いかな
You don't suppose this means something happened to Kamakiri-san?
これって　もしかして蟷螂さんの身に
No, no, no...
いやいや　蟷螂殿にかぎって
There's no way there's any opponent who could oppose Kamakiri-san's Ninpou: Tsume Awase.
あの人の忍法爪合わせが通じない相手なんて想像もつかねえぞ
殺人鬼が忍び装束着て歩いてるみたいな喰鮫殿だって
Even Kuizame, who was practically a murderer in a Ninja outfit, respected Kamakiri-dono.
蟷螂殿には一目置いていたんだ
Even without his Ninpou, that man has a wealth of experience.
忍法以前にあの人の経験はちょっとばかり半端じゃないんだぜ
蟷螂殿が負けるはずがねえって
There's no way he could lose!
I suppose...
そうですよね　臙脂水晶だって絶対ではありません
Those red crystals aren't a certain thing.
Right, right!
だよな 粉々に割れたところで
And there's been cases where the crystal shattered but the owner came back alive and well.
所有者がぴんぴんして戻っていた例もあるしな
いや　その話は僕も聞いたことがあるんですが
Well, I've heard that story too...
あれは誰かが間違って落っことして割っちゃったって ことだから
but I'm pretty sure that was just someone accidentally dropping and breaking it, so...
Um...
あのこの場合
In this situation, should we perhaps move with the assumption that Kamakiri-san has lost?
僕らは蟷螂さんの敗北を前提に動いた方が
いいんじゃないでしょうか
どうするつもりですか
What are you going to do?
If we go in order, I would be next, right?
順番的に次に行くのは僕ですよね
No, I'll go.
いや　俺が行く
じっくり休ませてもらったからな
I've rested for quite a bit now.
けれど　こういう場合僕の忍法の方が
But regardless of your condition, I think my skills would be more appropriate.
まだしも有効に作用すると思います
Your Ninpou is a little too... direct.
蝶々さんの忍法は　何というか　直接的過ぎます
You don't get it, Mitsubachi.
分かってくれや 蜜蜂
I really liked Kamakiri-dono!
俺は蟷螂殿が好きだったんだよ
I feel the same way!
そんなの僕だって同じです
And I'm fond of you too!
俺はお前も好きなんだよ
If there's to be one survivor in the Insect Squad, it should be you, the youngest of us.
虫組の中で　誰か１人生き残るんだとしたら
それは一番若いお前であるべきだと思う
But...
そんな
いいか
Got it?
お前は　俺と虚刀流の姉との戦いを離れた場所から観察していろ
Watch my battle with the Kyotouryuu girl from afar.
そして　もし俺が負けるようなことがあれば
And then, if I lose...
Use that information to abduct the girl.
それを踏まえてお前が娘を拉致するんだ
But...
しかしそれでは蝶々さんがかませ犬どころか犬死にになってしまいます
But then you would die like a dog!
Idiot.
バーカ
I don't intend to walk in there as a sacrifice or anything.
だから　俺は別に犠牲になって死ぬつもりはねえって
For all you know, I could just be saying all this to steal all the credit.
案外うまいこと言って
お前から手柄を横取りしようとしてるだけかもしんねえぜ
And "die like a dog"? We're the Insect Squad you know!
しかも　「犬死に」って俺ら虫組だぜ
But...
でも
You know, Mitsubachi...
あのさあ　蜜蜂
What?
何ですか
When this mission is over, I'm getting married.
この任務が終わったら俺　結婚するんだ
In our business there's no telling when or where we'll fall, so I'd never thought to take the plunge before...
いつ　どこで　命を落とすか分からん家業だから
これまで　踏み切れなかったが
But now I've decided.
俺　決めたんだ
I'm going to get married.
身を固めようって
I-Is that so...
そっ　そうだったんですか
To whom?
お相手は
Someone you know.
お前も知ってるやつだよ
勘のいいお前のことだ　うすうす感づいてたんじゃないのか
With instincts as good as yours, you should be able to figure it out.
えっ　いや
No...
She's another one of the 12 heads, Maniwa Oshidori of the Bird Squad.
同じ十二頭領の一人で
鳥組の真庭　鴛鴦だ
Oshidori-san?
鴛鴦さんですか　尻に敷かれそうですね
I get the feeling she'll be the dominant one.
だな
Right?
The Bird Squad is almost like a predator to the Insect Squad.
鳥組と虫組ってまるで捕食関係みてーだけどよ
I guess you could say my heart was eaten by her back then.
思えばあのとき俺の心はあいつに食われちまったのかもしれねーな
That was the start of our romance, but now it seems—
俺たちの馴れ初めってのがだ なこれまた笑っちゃ
蝶々さん
Chouchou-san, that's a nice story, but I think it might be better for you to stop...
いい話ですけど どうでしょう
そのあたりでやめておいた方が
Why?
何で
Never mind...
いや　とにかく分かりました
Anyway, we'll do that then.
You're up next so I'll leave it to you.
順番は蝶々さんにお譲りします
Though, I am a ninja you know.
しかし　僕だって忍びですやるからには徹底しますよ
If we're going to do this, we'll do it properly.
If anything happens to you, I won't provide any assistance.
何があろうと　助太刀に入ることはありません
For example, even if you're put through torture...
たとえ　蝶々さんがなぶられるような目に遭おうとも
ああ　そうしてくれ
Yeah, that's fine.
If it comes to that, I'll put up a futile resistance and increase the amount of intel for you.
そういう場合はせいぜい悪あがきして
お前が得られる情報を増やしてやるぜ
That was close.
危ねえ　危ねえ
I just quit smoking not long ago.
ちょっと前から　禁煙してるんだった
鴛鴦がすっげえ嫌煙家でさあ
Oshidori really despises smoking.
Even if you smoke outside, the smell gets on you, right?
外で吸っても　においつくだろ
Wouldn't Oshidori-san forgive you this one smoke just today?
鴛鴦さんも今日の１本くらいは許してくれるんじゃないですか
それは僕が預かっておきます
I'll take this for safekeeping.
任務完了の折りに心置きなく吸ってください
You can enjoy it at your leisure after the mission is over.
Mitsubachi...
蜜蜂　お前
I guess so.
そうだな
Ah right, keep this for me too.
おっ　そうだ
これも預かっといてくれ
後で一緒に吸おうぜ
We'll smoke together later.
たばこは
I don't...
Okay.
はい
Now then, I guess I'll be off.
さてと　行くとするか
Take this.
ほらよ
What for?
何ですか
The Insect Squad will always be together.
虫組はいつも一緒ってことだよ
Even in death, our bonds will never fray.
死んだ程度で俺たちの絆はほつれたりしねえ
You're an unexpectedly kind person deep down, aren't you?
何だ
蝶々さんって意外といい人だったんですね
Oh stop that.
よせ
あっ左胸に入れておくといいですよ
Put it in your left breast pocket.
What do you mean?
何だ　それ
Just do it please.
いいからそうしてください
All right.
分かったよ
じゃあな
Later then.
I hope that crystal...
あの水晶が
No, Kamakiri-san's soul...
いや　蟷螂さんの魂が蝶々さんを守ってくれるといいんですが
I hope his soul can protect Chouchou-san.
There's Ganryuu Island.
巌流島だ
How did you know?
どうして分かった
気配は完璧に消していたはずだがな
I thought I'd totally erased my presence....
I think it makes more sense for me to ask why you think you can erase your presence while you're still alive...
むしろわたしが聞きたいぐらいなのですけれど
どうして生きているくせに気配が消せるなどと
The person over there can only be the person over there, right?
そこにいる人はそこにいる人でしかないでしょう
自分はそこにいるのに自分探しなんてできないのと一緒です
It's the same reason you can't search for yourself, because you're right there.
Well, whatever.
まあいい
I am one of the 12 heads of the Maniwa Corps, Maniwa Chouchou.
俺は真庭忍軍十二頭領が一人
真庭蝶々だ
あんたをさらいに来た
I'm here to kidnap you.
That's quite a charming pickup line.
魅力的な口説き文句ですね
殿方にそんなせりふを言われる日が来るとはついぞ思いもしませんでした
I never thought I'd hear a line like that from a gentleman.
申し遅れました
I'm a bit late, and you probably already know, but for the sake of politeness I'll introduce myself.
すでにご存じでしょうが
一応礼儀ということで名乗らせていただきます
わたしは鑢家の家長
I am the head of the Yasuri household, Yasuri Nanami.
鑢七実と申します
Yes, I know.
ああ　知ってる
While you're here, could you tell me something?
せっかくだから教えてもらえますか
先ほどあなたと同じ服装をなさった方
Not long ago, another person with a similar outfit tried to attack me, but I didn't catch his name.
あの方のお名前は
He didn't introduce himself?
名乗らなかったのか
I didn't give him a chance to tell me.
聞く暇がありませんでした
あの人の名前は　真庭蟷螂だよ
His name was Maniwa Kamakiri.
Kamakiri...
蟷螂
ああ　だからつめが武器だったのですね
So that's why he used claws as weapons.
蟷螂殿を殺したか
Did you kill Kamakiri-dono?
Yes, he attacked me after all.
ええ　襲われたものですから
Oh that's right,
ああ　そうだそちらの人数を教えていただけますか
would you mind telling me how many of you there are?
What?
I actually tortured Kamakiri-san a bit, but he wouldn't tell me.
実は　軽く拷問したのですが
蟷螂さんは教えてくれなかったのですよ
You won't get any information out of me that Kamakiri-san didn't tell you.
蟷螂殿が教えなかったことを
この俺が教えるわけがないだろう
I see.
そうですか
Given your position as the one who defeated Kamakiri-dono, I'm not going to treat you as a woman.
蟷螂殿を倒したあんたを　俺は女だとは思わん
I will unreservedly go all out from the start against you.
遠慮会釈なく最初から本気でやらせてもらう
Depending on how it goes, I may even kill you.
場合によっては殺してしまうことになるかもしれんが
But then I can't be your hostage.
それでは人質になりませんよ
Of course, my priority is to take you hostage.
むろん人質にするのが何よりだが
姉の死体を目前にさらすだけでも
However, just displaying your corpse in front of your brother should diminish his fighting spirit considerably.
弟の戦意をそぐには十分だろう
I see.
なるほど
That's definitely ninja-like.
忍者らしいお言葉ですね
Though of course, if you'll surrender, I'll accommodate that.
とはいえもちろん降参に応じるつもりはあるんだぜ
If you think you're in a pinch, just say so.
ヤベえと思ったらいつでもいいから　声を上げなあ
As you see fit.
よしなに
That stance...
その構え
This is called Maniwa Kenpou.
これは　真庭拳法つってなあ
世間で出回ってるような一般的な拳法とはまったく起源を別にするものだ
It's completely different from the normal Kenpou that you usually see.
Maniwa Kenpou...
真庭拳法
The Kyotouryuu founder Yasuri Kazune and our founder once fought together, a long time ago.
虚刀流の開祖鑢一根と俺の初代とは
大昔に拳を交えたことがあるって話だからな
お前　知ってるか
Did you know?
いえ　全然知りませんでした
No, I had no idea.
Apparently it was a lot of fun.
そんときはずいぶんと楽しかったらしい
Why don't we fight like them, too?
俺らも負けずに戦おうぜ
What's wrong? Not taking a stance?
どうした構えないのか
As a fellow martial artist, I'd be honored to accept some instruction on it.
同じ拳法家としてぜひ ご指南いただきたいところなんだがな
I'll wait for you to take a stance.
俺は構えるまで待ってやるっつってんだぞ
That's generous of you, but I've never once in my life taken up a stance.
そうは言われましても
わたし今まで構えたことなんてありませんから
You mean Kyotouryuu has no stances?
虚刀流には構えがないってことなのか
だからわたしは虚刀流としては異端なのですよ
Actually, I'm a deviant as far as Kyotouryuu is concerned.
But think of it this way, Chouchou-san.
でもこう思いませんか　蝶々さん
構えるだなんて無駄なこと
Stances are useless to begin with.
何かあるたびにいちいち構えるなんて
If you change your stance in reaction to every little thing that happens, won't you become slower?
その分だけ　動作が遅れるじゃありませんか
あなたがそうであるよ
I can read exactly what you plan to do next from your stance.
構えることで
次にどうするつもりなのかだいたい読めてしまいますし
せっかくの謎の拳法も
You've already revealed to me any mysteries your Kenpou might have had.
結構底が透けちゃってますよ
そういうふうに構えるだけで
Just by taking that stance.
If I had to give mine a name,
それでも強いて名付けるとするなら
これは虚刀流　零の構え
it would be Kyotouryuu, zero dance: Fig tree.
無花果
と言ったところでしょうか
Or something like that.
Kyotouryuu: Poppy.
虚刀流
雛罌粟
Kyotouryuu:
Poppy
You dodged well.
よく避けられたなあ
Maniwa Kenpou and Maniwa Ninpou.
真庭拳法と真庭忍法
There are few people who've ever fended off this combination on the first try.
この合わせ技を最初の１回からかわせた奴は
あんまりいないんだけどな
Ninpou...
忍法
Ninpou: Ashigaru.
忍法足軽
My movements can ignore gravity.
俺の動きは重力を無視できるんだよ
I can hold any object, no matter how heavy,
どんな重い物でも持てるし
and even that thin branch would be more than enough to support me.
細い枝でも俺にとっちゃ十分過ぎるほど立派な足場になるんだ
No matter what kind of attack you throw at me,
あんたが俺の体にどんな攻撃を加えようと
俺はその方向へ吹っ飛ぶだけだ
I'll just fly off in the direction you're aiming.
わたしの手刀は実際には届いておらず
You're saying that my attack didn't actually hit,
and just before contact, your body was already set afloat by the air pressure from my hand?
その前に生じた風圧で
あなたの体はもう浮いていたということですか
That's right.
おうよ
You have quite the nerve to call yourself a martial artist while using such a bizarre technique.
そんな異形の技を使いながら
ひょうひょうと拳法家を名乗るとは
なかなかどうしてずぶとくていらっしゃる
Say what you like, but my Ninpou is my Ninpou so there's no helping that.
ずぶといと言われてもよ
それが俺の忍法なんだから仕方ねえじゃねえか
What now?
どうだい　降参するなら今が好機だぜ
If you want to surrender, now's a good opportunity.
Next time I'm going all out.
次は本気でいく
Didn't you say you were going all out from the start?
最初から本気だったはずなのでは
Don't you understand how amazing my Ninpou is?
あんた俺の忍法のすごさが分からねえのか
I understand.
分かりますよ
It's quite something.
十分すごいと思っています
It's a technique which cancels out your weight.
おそらくは重さを消失させる技ですか
その技を使って　お仲間と一緒にこの島にやって来たのでしょう
You used that technique to get you and your companions to this island, correct?
But what amazes me most is not the technique itself,
しかしわたしがそれよりもすごいと思っているのは技そのものじゃなくて
あなたがその技を習得するまでに掛けただろう時間のことですよ
but the amount of time it must have taken you to learn it.
生半可な努力ではなかったのでしょうね
I'm sure it took quite a bit of effort.
これまでの人生のほとんど全てを費やしたのでしょうね
I'm guessing it took almost your entire life to learn.
That Kamakiri-san also had his Ninpou: Tsume Awase.
あの蟷螂さんも忍法爪合わせとおっしゃっていましたが
自分の肉体をあそこまで改造するのに
That must also have taken a considerable amount of time, to reshape his body in order to be able to use that.
どれだけ時間を要したか
きっとそれは　真庭の里に遥か昔から延々と受け継がれて
That technique must have been passed down for centuries from generation to generation, perfecting it until it became complete.
ようやく完成した英知なのでしょうね
I'm quite...
わたしは　それが
Quite jealous of that.
わたしは　それが羨ましい
あなた方にはとうてい分からないのでしょうね
I'm sure that you of all people could never understand the feelings of someone who doesn't know what it feels like to make an effort.
努力することを許されない人間の気持ちなんて
Don't blame me if this kills you!
死んでも　知らねえぞ
また　見せてくれましたね
You kindly showed it to me again.
That woman just used Chouchou-san's Ninpou...
あの女　蝶々さんの忍法を
Ninpou: Ashigaru.
忍法足軽
It worked just like I expected.
やっぱり予想どおりでしたね
Of course, you can't cancel out your weight in reality.
当たり前ですけれど
実際に重さを消しているわけじゃない
N-No way...
そっ　そんなバカな
I've seen enough already, so out of mercy I'll kill you right now.
もう　十分見せてもらいましたから
一思いに殺してさしあげます
Kyotouryuu: Dandelion.
虚刀流
蒲公英
No way!
そんなっ
It can't be...
バカな
That's Tsume Awase!
爪合わせ
I wasn't able to use this Ninpou very well because I've only seen it once.
こちらの忍法は１回しか見せてもらえなかったから
あまりうまくいきませんでした
But next time I'm sure I'll do a little better.
まあ　次からはもう少しうまくいくでしょう
ああ　あり得ねえ
N-No way...
Learning the Maniwa Ninpou so easily...
真庭忍法をそんなにたやすく
お　俺たちがいったいどんな思いで
Do you know how much we went through...
Impossible...
あり得ねえ あり得ねえ あり得ねえ
Impossible, impossible!
Really...
本当
That's why I'm jealous.
だから羨ましいですよ
You're able to put effort into everything.
一々力一杯頑張れちゃって
Impossible...
そんな　嘘だ
No way!
Two Ninpou in such a short time...
こんな短時間で２人の忍法を
What on earth is that girl?
あの娘 いったい
I've been watching them.
見てきましたから　ずっと　わたしは
For a long time...
わたしの強さは例外的な強さ
My power is said to be exceptional and deviant.
反則的な強さと言われました
My father Mutsue tried to contain it as a father and as a swordsman.
父の六枝は父親として
あるいは一人の剣士として
それを封じ込めようとしたのです
That's why he didn't teach me Kyotouryuu at all.
だから　わたしには　一切虚刀流を教えてはくれなかった
How did I master the skills then?
では　なぜわたしがその技を会得しているのか
I was always watching them.
ずっと見ていたからです
I kept watching my younger brother continuously putting effort into it for 19 years.
弟の七花が努力する姿を
１９年間休まずに修行する弟の姿を
わたしはずっと見続けてきた
１回見れば大抵のことは覚えられます
I remember most skills by seeing them once.
２回見れば　盤石
I master them after the second time.
わたしの稽古は見稽古
My method of practice is observation.
Seeing is training for me.
わたしの修行は見ることなのです
ありがとうございます　わたしに見せてくれて
Thank you for showing me.
来るな　蜜蜂
Stay back, Mitsubachi!
But...
でも
You saw, right?
見てたろ　お前も
You need to come up with a proper plan!
だったら　ちゃんと戦略を立てろ
This woman...
この女 一筋縄ではいかねえぞ
You can't beat her by ordinary means!
Chouchou-san!
蝶々さん
The Insect Squad are...
虫組は　いつも一緒
always together...
I won't forgive you.
許さない
Now then...
さてと　この戦いはどこかから見られていたはずなんだけど
Someone was watching over this battle.
Isn't it time you came out?
そろそろ出てきませんか
She's ill?
病か
Then this is my chance!
ならば好機
Watch me, Kamakiri-san, Chouchou-san!
見ていてください蟷螂さん　蝶々さん
忍法
Ninpou: Makibishi Shidan!
撒菱指弾
Ninpou:
Makibishi Shidan
Got her!
仕留めた
I'm one of the 12 heads of the Maniwa Corps, Maniwa Mitsubachi.
僕は真庭忍軍十二頭領が一人
真庭蜜蜂です
I'm Yasuri... Nanami.
鑢 七実です
You killed two of my friends.
仲間を２人　殺してくれましたね
Yes, Kamakiri-san and... Chouchou-san, wasn't it?
ええ　蟷螂さんと蝶々さんとおっしゃいましたか
You needn't be so wary, as I'm the last one.
周りを警戒しなくとも僕が最後の一人ですよ
Though I think I'm more than enough to take you in your present condition.
まあ　今のあなたに対するのならば
僕一人だけでも十分過ぎるほど十分でしょうけれどね
Is this poison?
毒 ですか
Yes, it's poison.
ええ　毒です
Don't worry, it's not a lethal one.
ご安心ください 死ぬほどの毒ではありません
What we want isn't you, but rather your brother.
僕の目的はあなたじゃない
あなたの弟さんです
To be precise, we want the completed Shikizaki Kiki Deviant Blades which your brother is collecting.
もっと言えば
あなたの弟さんが集めている四季崎記紀の完成形変体刀です
That said, personally I really want to kill you.
本音を言えばあなたを殺してしまいたい気持ちはあるんですがね
But if I do that, I'll only be able to satisfy my own wish for vengeance.
しかしそうすることで晴れるのは
みすみす仲間を殺されてしまった僕の無念だけでしょう
I'll only truly be able to avenge Kamakiri-san and Chouchou-san by collecting the swords.
蟷螂さんや　蝶々さんの無念は
刀集めを達成してこそ晴らせるというものです
You talk a lot.
よく　しゃべりますね
People really do tend to talk a lot when they have the advantage.
やはり人は自分が優位に立ったときこそ饒舌になるものなのですね
I suppose even Ninja are no exception.
忍びといえどそれは例外ではありませんか
What about you?
あなたこそ
I said the poison isn't lethal, but at this point you shouldn't be able to talk.
死なないとは言っても
普通もうしゃべれなくなってもおかしくないくらいの毒なんですけど
Perhaps I should hit you with another for good measure.
念のためもう一発くらい撃ち込んでおいた方がいいのでしょうか
Is that your Ninpou?
それが　あなたの忍法ですか
Yes, it's called Ninpou: Makibishi Shidan.
ええ　忍法　撒菱指弾といいます
Are you sure you should be showing me that move?
その技　わたしに見せてしまっていいのですか
I don't mind what you see in your current state.
今のあなたなら何を見られても平気ですね
たとえ　あなたが言語道断空前絶後の天才なのだとしても
You can't do anything, even if you are an unprecedented level of genius.
I'd prefer it if you'd obediently submit, as the gentleman in me would like to avoid scarring that beautiful skin of yours.
それに　おとなしく僕に従っていただけるようなら
僕も一人の男として
あなたの美しい肌に傷を付けるのは忍びないと思います
Well, thank you.
それは
どうも
I look at things objectively.
僕は物事を客観的に見る
あなたが僕なんかよりもずっと腕の立つ人間であることは承知しています
I understand that you're far stronger than I am.
That being the case, I should at least cut off your arms while I can.
ならば今の内に両腕を切り落としておく位のことはしておくべきでしょう
それほどの痛みはないはずです
It shouldn't hurt much.
貴方の全身を巡る毒がちょうどいい痛み止めの役割をしてくれるでしょう
The poison flowing through your veins now should serve well as a painkiller.
Please don't think badly of me.
悪く思わないでください
It's your fault for being too strong.
あなたが強過ぎるのが悪いんですから
いっ　いつの間に
W-When did you...
Ninpou: Ashigaru...
忍法　足軽それと　そう　撒菱指弾
And yes, Makibishi Shidan.
A caltrop?
撒菱
There's no way you had any caltrops prepared beforehand!
あなたが撤菱を持っているだなんて
そんな設定ここまでのどこにも登場していない
あなたがくれたではないですか　２個も
But you gave them to me.
Two of them.
し　しかし
B-But...
肉に食い込んだ撒菱がそう簡単に引き抜けるはずがない
There's no way that a caltrop dug into your flesh could come out so easily!
とげに　返しが付いているんですから！
There are hooks on the prongs!
ですから　このつめで肉ごとえぐり取りました
Yes, so I dug it out with these claws, flesh and all.
くっ ど 毒は
W-What about the poison...
Oh, that was an act.
ああ　あれは演技ですよ
An... act?
演技
A little poison that isn't even lethal means nothing to me.
死にもしない程度の毒なんて何でもありません
そんなものはわたしにとっては　日常です
That's an everyday experience for me.
Everyday?
日常
No matter how excruciating, no matter how painful, no matter how close I am to death,
どれだけ苦しくても どれだけ痛くても どれだけ死にそうでも
わたしの体は死を選びません
my body just won't choose death.
いえ　死を許されないんです
Or rather, it won't allow me to die.
Why isn't she dead yet?
どうして死なないのか分からない
この子はどうして生きているのだろう　本当にかわいそう
It's so pitiful...
She may die at any time...
いつ死んでもおかしくない というか
どうしてまだ死なないのか分かりません
Or rather, I don't know why she hasn't already died yet.
Why is she still alive?
どうしてまだ生きているのか
Even though she's in so much pain...
こんなに苦しそうなのに　かわいそう
Unable to even die peacefully...
本当に楽に　死ねもしないなんて
It hurts, just let me...
苦しい
いっそ　死んでしまえたら
If only she'd just die...
If she could just die, she'd be at peace.
死ぬことができれば楽になれるのに
That's why I'm jealous of you people, who can feel pain from a little bit of poison.
だからその程度の毒で痛みや苦痛を感じるあなたがうらやましい
Not yet! I haven't lost yet!
まだだ　まだ　負けたわけじゃない
If you're able to bear this poison, there's no way I can't!
貴様に　耐えられるような毒に僕が耐えられないわけがない
No, I doubt you can.
いいえ　無理だと思いますよ
あなたの肩に撃ち込んだその撒菱なのですけれど
That caltrop I hit your shoulder with contained another poison, on top of the one you already had on it.
あなたが最初から塗っていた毒の上から
さらに　わたしが別の毒を塗っておきましたから
最初に蟷螂さんが奥歯に仕込んでいた物を使わせてもらいました
I used the poison from Kamakiri-san's molar.
そういう設定はちゃんと登場していましたよね
I did have that prepared beforehand, right?
Since you have the choice, could you tell me what you'd prefer?
せっかくですから選んでいただけませんか
Choice?
選ぶ
Will you die by poison or by the sword?
毒で死ぬか刀で死ぬか
あなたのおかげで
Thanks to you, I've seen how to use a sword for the first time in my life.
わたし生まれて初めて刀の使い方を見せてもらいましたから
刀で 殺してください
Slay me by the sword please...
If I died by suicide poisoning, I wouldn't be able to face my comrades in the next life.
自決の毒で死んだなど
仲間に顔向けできません
分かりました
Understood.
Then I will show you Kyotouryuu's 8th and final secret move as a farewell gift.
では　はなむけに
虚刀流の八番目最終奥義をお見せしましょう
Before that...
その前に
I beg a favor of you.
お願いがあります
C-Could you bury...
ぼ 僕の死体をみんなと同じ場所へ埋めてくだ
my corpse along with...
my companions?
That's fine.
いいです
And... this too...
よそれとこれを
What's that?
何です　それ
That really was one tough battle though.
しかし　それにしても大変な戦いだった
ああ　大変な戦いだった
Yeah, it really was.
さすが日本最強だ
He was true to his title as Japan's strongest.
錆白兵　俺はその名を生涯忘れることはないだろう
Sabi Hakuhei... I won't forget that name for the rest of my life.
まさに紙一重の勝利だった
You won by the skin of your teeth.
聖地巌流島にまた新しい歴史が刻まれたといっても過言ではないな
It's no exaggeration to say that we made new history on the holy island of Ganryuu.
首の皮一枚の戦いとはまさにあのことだ
It was definitely a close battle.
とがめの作戦がなかったら今ごろ俺は生きちゃいないだろう
Without your strategy, I wouldn't be alive now.
What are you talking about?
何を言う　そなたの剣技があってこそのわたしの奇策だ
My strategies don't mean anything without your skills.
わたしはそなたのことを見直したぞ
I've revised my opinion of you now!
And I've fallen for you all over again.
俺はとがめにほれ直したぜ
Oh stop that.
言うな　言うな
しかし　まあ錆白兵と１対１で剣技を競い打ち勝ったのだ
But you really competed with Sabi Hakuhei in swordplay and won.
Now you've truly earned the title of "Japan's strongest" that you wanted.
これでそなたは名実ともに欲しがっていた
日本最強の称号を手にしたのではないか
Japan's strongest, huh...
日本最強か
あまり実感はないがな
It hasn't really sunk in yet.
それにしても　錆が披露した数々の剣技には
But each of the various techniques Sabi unveiled to us...
心の底から驚かされたぜ
they all really caught me by surprise.
立ち合いの最初から見せたあの移動法　爆縮地
The movement technique he used at the start of our duel —
Bakushukuchi — that shocked me.
あれはびっくりだ
まさか杜若よりも自在な足運びがあったとはな
I never imagined that he could have more flexible footwork than Kyotouryuu's Iris.
Skewered rice dumplings for two, please!
団子を２皿頼む
はい ただ今
Yes, right away!
技というならわたしはあれだな
Speaking of techniques, that one caught me off guard —
刀の柄とさやを使用しての逆転夢斬が印象深い
that "Gyakuten Muzan" one where he used the sword and sheath together was really impressive.
あの技を会得した際に錆は剣聖の称号を得たというがまさにしかり
I can completely understand why he gained the title of "Holy Swordsman" after learning that technique.
No no, that wizardry which allowed him to freely change the length of the blade — Sokuchiken —
刀の刃渡りその伸縮を自由自在にできるというあの妙技
速遅剣こそ　虚刀流にとっては脅威だった
that was a true threat to my Kyotouryuu.
Being a sword of fixed length myself, it was impossible to judge his timing.
何せ　固定された刀でありながら
間合いのはかりようがないってんだから
あのとき偶然俺の足場が崩れていなかったらと思うとぞっとするぜ
I shudder when I think what would have happened if I hadn't lost my footing then...
お待たせしました
Sorry to keep you waiting!
決まるかと思ったそなたの手刀の切っ先を完全に見切ったあの受け太
And the way he caught your blade when I thought you were about to land a blow on him...
刀刃取りも圧巻だった
It was quite magnificent.
勝ちはしたものの
Even though we won, I'm certain we only faced a fraction of that fallen swordsman's true power.
わたしたちは　おそらく
あの堕剣士の恐しさの一分も味わってはおらんのだろう
You're probably right.
そうだな
正直言って勝った気がしない
Honestly, I don't really feel like I won.
We probably can't even say we were lucky in that battle.
今回の戦いは残念ながら運が良かったとさえ言えないぜ
まったくもってそのとおりだ
You're absolutely right.
わたしたちはただ負けなかったにすぎん
We just managed not to lose.
Sweet red bean soup for two, please!
ぜんざいを２人前頼む
Certainly!
はい
そして何よりの白眉は
And it goes without saying that his masterpiece was that "Hakutou Kaigan" technique,
言うまでもなく四季崎記紀の完成形変体刀十二本が１本
only made possible by Hakutou Hari, the Shikizaki Kiki Completed Deviant Blade that he carried.
「薄刀·針」だからこそ実現したあの奥義　薄刀開眼だろうな
まさか見た目の美麗さのみが取りえの
I never dreamed that Hakutou might have had such an amazing attribute.
もろく弱いだけの刀だと思ったが
あんな利点と特性があったとは夢にも思わなかったぜ
I thought it was just a frail sword, with beauty as its only saving grace.
俺は初めて剣士の怖さを思い知った気がする
I feel like I've learned the true horror of that swordsman.
あちっ
Hot!
That's true.
そうだな
錆の剣は空に浮かぶ太陽すら切り裂くというあの触れ込み
It was rumored that Sabi's sword could slice even the sun in half.
あの奥義ならば
With that technique, it doesn't sound like such a far fetched idea.
それも不可能ではないのかもしれぬ
However!
されどだ過程はどうあれ
Regardless of the process, we managed to obtain Hakutou.
わたしたちは結果として薄刀を手にしたのだ
錆白兵を正面からの果たし合いで打ち破ったこと
You should be proud of the fact that you defeated Sabi Hakuhei face to face in a duel!
これは誇るべきことだぞ
かもしれねえ
I probably should.
だがそれにしてもやつが死に際に言っていたせりふが気になるぜ
But what he said on the verge of death bothers me.
俺が
That I'm...
No, that Kyotouryuu was left behind by Shikizaki Kiki.
否　虚刀流が四季崎記紀の遺品だとは
いったい　どういう意味なんだ
What does that mean?
記紀の血統とは　いったい
And what does he mean by "Kiki's bloodline"?
錆は自分のことを出来損ないの失敗作だと言っていたが
Sabi even called himself an incomplete failed creation...
あいつは　刀の毒に侵されて
Didn't you say he betrayed you after being poisoned by the sword?
とがめを裏切ったんじゃなかったのか
分からん
I don't know.
刀の毒に侵されていたこと自体はまず間違いはないが
I'm pretty confident he was affected by the sword's poison,
ひょっとすると
but Sabi might have had his own unavoidable circumstances.
錆には錆でよんどころなき事情があったのやもしれぬ
それもやつの言葉を信じるなら
If we're to believe what he said, it should all become clear as we continue our journey.
旅を続けるうちに明らかになるのであろう
Hot!
あちっ
I suppose.
そうだな
「薄刀·針」も無事に割ることもなく
We managed to obtain Hakutou Hari without snapping it, breaking it, or even scratching it.
壊すこともなく傷一つ付けずに収集することができたし
これで　変体刀も　４本目
With our fourth sword in hand, the end is starting to come into sight.
ちょっと終わりが見えてきたんじゃねえか
気持ちは分かるが調子に乗るものではないぞ
I understand how you feel, but don't get carried away.
旅はまだまだこれからだ
There's still a long way left to our journey.
そうだなせっかく九州まで来たのだ
Let's see, since we came all the way to Kyuushuu, let's collect another sword while we're on a roll.
景気づけにもう１本変体刀を収集するとしよう
ああ　分かった
All right.
異論はねえぜ
No objections here.
で　次の場所は
So, where next?
次なる目的地は薩摩だ
Our next destination is Satsuma.
Our next target is Zokutou Yoroi, which boasts an unparalleled absolute defense.
収集対象は絶対無双の防御を誇る「賊刀·鎧」
対戦相手は海賊船の船長だ
Your opponent is the captain of a pirate ship.
Red bean soup and dumplings for two please!
ぜんざいと団子を２人前追加だ
Okay!
はーい
こうして　鑢七花は錆白兵を打ち破り
And so Yasuri Shichika defeated Sabi Hakuhei, obtaining the title of Japan's strongest.
名実ともに日本最強剣士の名を襲名いたしました
ただし　それはあくまでも暫定最強剣士の座なのでございます
However, the position of strongest swordsman is but a provisional one.
Sabi Hakuhei, huh...
錆白兵か
He wasn't as strong as Nee-chan though.
それでも姉ちゃんほどじゃなかったな
And thus the Insect Squad was wiped out on Fushou island.
真庭虫組　不承島にて全滅
蝶のように舞い
Dancing like a butterfly, stinging like a bee, consuming like a praying mantis...
蜂のように刺し
蟷螂のように食らい
and dying like a bug.
虫のように死んだ
Really Shichika, you call that an ultimate move?
七花ったら　何が最終奥義よ
大口たたいちゃって
For all that boasting, it has a huge weak point.
あの技　とんでもない弱点があるじゃない
You really can't call that a real move.
奥義だなんてとても言えないわ
使ってみないと分からないものね
You can't tell these things till you've tried it out.
早く教えてあげないと　あの子大変なことになりかねないけど
I'd better tell him as soon as possible, or he might end up getting in trouble.
どうしたものかしら
What should I do...
わたしも交ぜてもらおうかな　刀集め
Maybe I should join them in the sword hunt.
Now, although this episode probably raised some eyebrows, the story of Katanagatari for this month and this evening ends here.
さて　題目そのものに突っ込みどころ満載な
今月こよいの『刀語』お楽しみはここまでにございます
soyokaze manimani chiru hana wa
Blossoms flying around in a gentle breeze
その風まにまに散る花らは
utsushiku kanbina yume
are beautiful sweet dreams
美しく甘美な夢
浮世に許されざる
ukiyoni yurusarezaru
embracing unforgivable emptiness
虚無をたいて
kyomu wo daite
in this transient world
誰も辿りつくことのない
dare mo tadoritsuku koto no nai
Nothing has reflection
暗闇には何も映らない
kurayami ni wa nani mo utsuranai
in the darkness which no one reaches
ちらりしみてゆく絶望も
jiwari shimiteyuku zetsubou mo
Even despair piercing me little by little
先の国に消え
sen no doku ni magure
is diverted by a thousand poisons
錆白兵
Sabi Hakuhei was a tough foe.
恐ろしい敵だった
Although it didn't really feel like we won,
しかし　まったく勝った気がしないとはいえ
a victory is a victory.
勝ちは勝ちだ　勝ちなんだもん
We did win!
The next place I and "Japan's strongest" Shichika head for is Satsuma.
日本最強を手に入れた　七花と私が向かう次の目的地は薩摩
How do we fight a pirate captain with a gang of pirates at his command?
組織力を持つ厄介な海賊団の船長相手にどう戦う
え？何？一目ぼれ？
What? He fell for me at first sight?
俺の女になれだとう？！
"Please be my woman"?
What??
Zokutou
Yoroi
次　次回　刀語　「賊刀·鎧」　チリよ
N-Next time on Katanagatari: Zokutou Yoroi.
Cheerio!